<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble petition of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament presented to His Majestie at York the seventeenth of June, 1642 with His Majesties answer thereunto.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22010</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10268617</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204627</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248501575</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1573A</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10268617</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22010)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204627)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1382:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble petition of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament presented to His Majestie at York the seventeenth of June, 1642 with His Majesties answer thereunto.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Barker and by the assignes of John Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204627:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204627:1"/>
            <p>The humble PETITION OF The Lords and Commons Assembled in Parliament. Presented to His Majestie at York, the seventeenth of June, 1642. VVith His Majesties Answer thereunto.</p>
            <p>YORK: Printed by ROBERT BARKER, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Majestie: And by the Assignes of JOHN BILL. 1642.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204627:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204627:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS <hi>MOST EXCELLENT</hi> MAJESTIE. The humble Petition of the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Majesties most humble and faithfull Subjects, the Lords and Commons assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament, have late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received a Petition from a great number of the Gentry, Freeholders, and other Inhabitants of the County of <hi>York,</hi> assembled there, by your Majesties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, the third of June; wherein they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto Us, That having taken a Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to addresse themselves unto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie, in the humble way of a Petition for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204627:3"/> redresse of those Grievances which they now lie under, they were violently interrupted and affronted therein by the Earle of <hi>Lynsey,</hi> the Lord <hi>Savile,</hi> and others; and, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all the means they could use to present their just desires to your Majestie, yet they could not prevail with your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie to accept of their Petition, the Copie whereof they have sent to us, with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble desire, That we would take such course therein, as may tend to the preservation of their Liberties, and the Peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and that we would addresse our selves to your Majestie in their behalf, that by our means their desires may finde better accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with your Majestie. Whereupon, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving seriously weighed and considered the particulars of those their complaints and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, as they are laid down in their Petition, and finding that the Grievances they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of, are the increase of the miseries for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly sustained by that County (which hath wel-nigh, for three yeers last past, been the tragicall Stage of Armies and War) by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of your Majesties distance in Residence, and difference in Councels from your great
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204627:3"/> Councell, the Parliament, begetting great distempers and distractions thorowout the Kingdom, and especially in that County; The drawing to those parts great numbers of discontented persons, that may too justly be feared, do affect the publike ruine for their private advantage; The drawing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of many Companies of the Trained Bands, and others, both Horse and Foot of that County, and retaining multitudes of Commanders and Cavaliers from other parts; The dayly resort of Recusants to your Majesties Court at <hi>York;</hi> The great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Arms, and other warlike Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the great terrour and amazement of your Majesties peaceable Subjects, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a great decay of Trade and Commerce amongst them; All and every of which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars are against the Law, which your Majestie hath made so many, and so fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent professions to uphold and maintain: And the Lords and Commons finding, on the other side, their humble desires to be, That your Majestie would hearken to your Parliament, and declining all other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels whatsoever, unite your Confidence to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204627:4"/> your Parliament; And that your Majestie would not divide your Subjects joynt-duty to your Majestie, the Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nor destroy the essence of your great Councell and highest Court, by subjecting the Determinations and Councels thereof to the counsels and opinions of any private persons whatsoever; That your Majestie having passed an Act, That this Parliament shall not be dissolved but by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, your Majestie would not do any thing tending thereunto, by commanding away the Lords and great Officers, whose attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is necessary thereunto; That your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie having expressed your confidence in the Affections of that County, you would please to dismisse your extraordinary Guards, and the Cavaliers, and others of that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, who seem to have little interest or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the publike good, their language and behaviour speaking nothing but divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and war, and their advantage consisting in that which is most destructive to others: And lastly, That in such Consultations and Propositions as your Majestie maketh to that County, such may not be thrust upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204627:4"/> them, as Men of that County, that neither by their Fortune or Residence are any part of it: All which their humble &amp; most just desires, being according to Law, which your Majestie hath so often declared should be the Measure and Rule of your Government and Actions. And we, your Majesties most faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects the Lords and Commons fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with the Gentlemen and others of the County of <hi>York,</hi> in their Assurance that those desires of theirs will abundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the Glory of God, the honour and safety of your Majestie, the good of your Posterity, and the Peace and prosperity of this Kingdom:</p>
            <p>We humbly beseech your Majestie gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously to hearken unto them, and to grant them; And that you would joyne with your Parliament in a speedy and effectuall course for the preservation of their Liberties, and the Peace of the Kingdom; which duty, as we are now called upon by that County to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, so do we stand engaged to God and Man for the performance thereof, by the Trust reposed in us, and by our solemne Vow and Protestation. And your Majestie, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204627:5"/> with us, stands engaged by the like Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of Trust, and of an Oath, besides the many and earnest Professions and Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which your Majestie hath made to this purpose to your whole Kingdom in generall, and to that County in particular, the Peace and quiet of the Kingdom, (as is well obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by those Gentlemen, and Free-holders of York-shire, in their Petition) being the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly visible means, under God, wherein consists the Preservation of the Protestant Religion, the Redemption of our Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the happinesse, and prosperitie of your Majestie, and of all your Dominions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:204627:5"/>
            <head>❧ His Majesties Answer to the aforesaid Petition.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Majestie having carefully weighed the matter of this Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, presented to Him at <hi>York,</hi> on Friday the seventeenth of Iune, by the Lord <hi>Howard,</hi> Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmeley,</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> though he might refer the Petitioners to his two last Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, wherein most of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in this Petition are fully answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or might refuse to give any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer at all, till He had received satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in those high Indignities He hath so often complained of, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Iustice for: Yet, that all the world may see how desirous His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204627:6"/> is to leave no Act, which seems to carry the Reputation of both His Houses of Parliament, and in the least degree to reflect upon His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Iustice and Honour unanswer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is graciously pleased to return this Answer:</p>
            <p>THat if the Petition mentioned to be presented to both Houses of Parliament, had been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to this now delivered to Him, His Majestie might have discerned the number and the qualitie of the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, which His Majestie hath great reason to beleeve, was not in truth so considerable as is pretended; for His Majestie assures you, That He hath never refused any Petition so attested as that would be thought to be. But His Majestie well remembers, That on the third of Iune, when there was, upon His Majesties Summons, the greatest &amp; the most cheerfull concourse of people that ever was beheld of one County, appearing before Him at <hi>York,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:204627:6"/> a Gentleman (one Sir <hi>Thomas Fayre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax)</hi> offered, in that great Confluence, a Petition to His Majestie, which His Majestie seeing to be avowed by no man but himself, and the generall and universall Acclamations of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple seeming to disclaim it, did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, conceiving it not to be of so pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like a nature as to be fit to be present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or received in that place: And His Majestie is most confident (and in that must appeal to those who were then present) that what ever the substance of that Petition was, it was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to by any considerable number of Gentrie or Free-holders of this Countie; but solicited by a few, mean, inconsiderable persons, and disliked and visibly discountenanced by the great body of the known Gentry, Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, and Inhabitants of this whole Countie. And if the matter of that Petition were such as is suggested in this, His Majestie hath great reason to beleeve it was framed and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (as many others of such nature
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204627:7"/> have been) in <hi>London,</hi> not in Yorkshire. For sure no Gentleman of quality and understanding, of this County, would talk of His great preparations of Arms, and other warlike Provisions, to the great terrour and amazement of His peaceable Subjects, when they are witnesses of the violent taking His Arms from Him, and stopping all wayes for bringing more to Him; And if there were no greater terrour and amazement of His Majesties peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Subjects in other places by such preparations and provisions, there would be no more cause to complain of a great decay of Trade and Commerce there, then is in this place: But His Majestie hath so great an assurance of the fidelitie and generall affections of His good Subjects of this Countie (which He hopes will prove exemplar over His whole Kingdom) that He hath great cause to beleeve, That they do rather complain of His Majesties confidence, and of His slownesse, that whilst there is such endeavour abroad
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204627:7"/> to raise Horse, and to provide Arms against His Majestie, and that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour put in execution, His Majestie trusts so much to the Iustice of His cause, and the affections of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and neglects to provide strength to assist that Iustice, and to protect those affections. For any affronts offered by the Earle of <hi>Lindsey</hi> and the Lord <hi>Savile,</hi> to those who intended to petition His Majestie, His Majestie wishes that both His Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament would have examined that Information, and the credit of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, with that gravity and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, as in cases which concern the Innocence and Honour of persons of such quality hath been accustomed, before they had proscribed two Peers of the Realm, and exposed them (as much as in them lay) to the rage and fury of the people, under the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of being Enemies to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, a brand newly found out (and of no legall signification) to incense the people by, and with which the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204627:8"/> simplicity of former times was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted: And then His Majestie hath some reason to beleeve they would have found themselves as much abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the report concerning those Lords, as he is sure they are in those which tell them of the resort of great numbers of discontented persons to him, and of the other particulars, mentioned to be in that Petition: Whereas they who observe what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort is here to His Majestie, well know it to be of the prime Gentlemen of all the Counties in <hi>England,</hi> whom nothing but the love of Religion, the care of the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom, besides their affection to His Person, could engage into great journeys, trouble, and expence, men of as precious reputation, and as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary lives as this Nation hath any; whose assistance His Majestie knows He must not expect, if He should have the least designe against Honour and Iustice; and such witnesses His Majestie desires to have of all His ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:204627:8"/>
            <p>For the declining all other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and the uniting His Confidence to His Parliament, His Majestie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires both His Houses of Parliament seriously and sadly to consider, That it is not the name of a great or little Councell that makes the Results of that Councell Iust or Vnjust, Neither can the Imputation upon His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, of not being advised by His Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, (especially since all their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all their Orders are exposed to the publike view) long mis-lead His good Subjects, except in truth they see some particular sound Advice, necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Peace and Happinesse of the Common-wealth, dis-esteemed by His Majestie; and such an Instance He is most assured, neither can, nor shall be given: And that they will think it merit in His Majestie, from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, to reject such Councell as would perswade Him to make Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self none of the Three Estates, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up His negative voyce, to allow them a Power superiour to that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204627:9"/> which the Law hath given Him, whensoever it pleaseth the Major part, present, of both Houses, to say, That He doth not discharge His Trust, as He ought, and to subject His, and His Subjects unquestiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Right and Proprietie to their Votes, without, and against Law, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the meer pretence of necessitie. And His Majestie must appeal to all the world, who it is that endeavours to divide the joynt duty of His Subjects; His Majestie, who requires nothing but what their own duty, guided by the infallible Rule of the Law, leades them to do; or they, who, by Orders and Votes (opposite and contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Law, Custom, President, and Reason) so confound the Affertions and Vnderstandings of His good Subjects, that they know not how to behave themselves with honesty and Safety, whilest their Conscience will not suffer them to submit to the one, nor their Securitie to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the other.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204627:9"/>
            <p>It is not the bare saying, That His Majesties Actions are against the Law (with which He is reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Petition, as if He departed from His often Protestations to that purpose) must conclude Him, there being no one such particular in that Petition alleadged, of which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie is in the least degree guilty: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the same reverence and esteem be paid by you to the Law, (except your own Votes be judge) needs no other evidence then those many, very many Orders published in print, both concerning the Church and State, those long imprisonments of severall persons, without hearing them, upon generall information, and the great unlimited Fees to your Officers, worse then the imprisonment, and the Arbitrary Censure upon them when they are admitted to be heard; let the Law be judge by whom it is violated.</p>
            <p>For that part of the Petition which seems to accuse His Majestie of a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to dissolve this Parliament (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204627:10"/> to the Act for the Continuance) by commanding away the Lords and great Officers, whose attendance is necessary, which His Majestie well knows to be a new Calumnie, by which the grand Contrivers of ruine for the State, hope to seduce the minds of the People from their Affection to, or into Iealousie of his Majestie, as if He meant this way to bring this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (which may be the case of all Parliaments) to nothing: It is not possible for His Majestie more to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse his Affection to, and his Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Freedom, Libertie, and frequencie of Parliaments, then He hath done: And who ever considers how visible it must be to His Majestie, That it is impossible for Him to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist, without the Affections of His people, and that those Affections can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not possibly be preserved, or made use of, but by Parliaments, cannot give the least credit, or have the least suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that his Majestie would chuse any other way to the happinesse He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204627:10"/> for Himself and His Posteritie, but by Parliaments.</p>
            <p>But for His calling the Lords hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or any others absenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, who have not been called; who ever considers the Tumults (which no Votes or Declaration can make to be no Tumults) by which His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie was driven away, and many Members of either House in danger of their lives; The demanding the names of those Lords who would not consent to their Propositions by Message from the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, delivered at the Bar by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Hollis,</hi> with that most tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Petition in the name of many thousands (among many other of the same kinde) directed to the House of Commons, and sent up by them to the House of Lords, taking notice of the prevalencie of a Malignant facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which made abortive all their good Motions, which tended to the Peace and Tranquilitie of the Kingdom, desiring, That those noble Worthies of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204627:11"/> the House of Peers, who concurred with them in their happy Votes, might be earnestly desired to joyn with that honourable House, and to sit and Vote as one entire Body; professing, That unlesse some speedie remedie were taken for the removall of all such Obstructions as hindred the happy progresse of their great endeavours, their Petitioners should not rest in quietnesse, but should be inforced to lay hold on the next remedie which was at hand to remove the disturbers of their Peace, and (want and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie breaking the bounds of modestie) not to leave any means unassayed for their relief; Adding, that the cry of the poor and needy was, That such persons who were the Obstacles of their peace, and hinderers of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py proceedings of this Parliament, might be forthwith publikely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whose removall, they conceived, would put a period to these distracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Vpon which, a great number of Lords departing, the Vote, in order
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204627:11"/> to the Ordinance concerning the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> was immediately passed, though it had been twice before put to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion and rejected by the Votes of much the major part of that House. And who ever considers the strange Orders, Votes and Declarations which have since passed, to which whosoever would not consent, that is, with freedom and libertie of Language professe against, was in danger of censure and imprisonment, will not blame Our care in sending for them, or theirs in coming, or absenting themselves from being involved in such Conclusions. Neither will it be any objection that they stayed there long after any tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults were, and therefore that the tumults drave them not away. If every day produced Orders and Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions as illegall as, and indeed, but the effects of the tumults, there was no cause to doubt the same power would be ready to prevent any oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition to those Orders after they were made, which had made way and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204627:12"/> for the proposition of them, and so whosoever conceived himself in danger of future tumults (against which there is not the least provision) was driven away by those which were past. And his Majestie hath more reason to wonder at those who stay behinde, after all His legall Power is voted from him, and all the people told, That He might be with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty and duty enough deposed, then any man hath at those who have been willing to withdraw themselves from the place where such desperate and dangerous Positions are avowed. Which his Majestie doth not menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with the least thought of lessen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the power or validity of any Act to which He hath given his Assent this Parliament, all and every of which He shall as inviolably observe, as He looks to have his own Rights preserved, but to shew by what means so many strange Orders have of late been made; and to shew how earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Majestie desires to be present at,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204627:12"/> and receive advice from both Houses of Parliament, (against whom it shall never be in the power of a Malignant party to incense his Majestie) his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie again offers his Consent, That both Houses may be adjourned to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place which may be thought convenient, where his Majestie will be present, and doubts not but the Members of either House will make a full Appearance, and even the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission which must attend such an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journment, may not be the least means of recovering that temper which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for such debates.</p>
            <p>And this His Majestie conceives to be so very necessary, that if the Mindes and Inclinations of every Member of either House were equally composed, the Licence is so great, that the mean People about <hi>London</hi> and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs have taken, that both for the Libertie and Dignitie of Parliament, that Convention for a time should be in another place. And sure, how much soever the safety and security of this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204627:13"/> Kingdom depends on Parliaments, it will never be thought, that those Parliaments must of necessitie be at <hi>Westminster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majesties Confidence is no lesse then He hath expressed, (and hath great Cause to expresse) in the Affections of this County, an instance of which Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections all men know, His Guard (which is not extraordinary) to be, and wonders that such a Legall Guard, at His own charge, for His Person, (within twenty Miles of a Rebellion, and of an Army in Pay against Him) should be objected by those, who for so many Moneths, and in a Place of known, and confessed Securitie, have without and against Law, kept a guard for themselves, at the Charge of the Common-wealth, and upon that stock of money which was given for the Relief of the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and bleeding Condition of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or the payment of the great debt due to Our Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Resort of Papists to the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204627:13"/> Court, his Majesties great Care for the prevention thereof, is notoriously known; That when he was informed two or three of His intended Guard were of that Religion, He gave speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all direction, with expressions of His displeasure, That they should be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly discharged, and provided that no Person should attend on Him under that Relation, but such as took the Oaths of Allegiance and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy; That He commanded the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe to proceed with all severitie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law, against all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists that should come within five Miles of the Court; and if, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing this, there be any Papists neer the Court, (which his Majestie as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures you He knows not, nor hath heard, but by this Petition) He doth hereby command them to depart; and declares to all Officers, and Ministers of Iustice, that they shall proceed strictly against them, according to the Law, and as they will answer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary at their perils.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:204627:14"/>
            <p>For the language and behaviour of the Cavaliers (a word, by what mistake soever it seems, much in disfavour) there hath not been the least Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint here; and therefore 'tis probable the fault was not found in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Neither can his Majestie imagine what is meant by the mention of any men thrust upon them, in such Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultations and Propositions as his Majestie makes to this County, who are neither by their Fortune or Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, any part of it; and therefore can make no Answer to it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, his Majestie assures you, He hath never refused to receive any Petition, (whether you have or no, your selves best know) and will consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what reputation it will be to you of Iustice or Ingenuitie to receive all Petitions, how senslesse and scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous soever, of one kinde, under the pretence of understanding the good peoples minds and affections, and not onely refuse the Petition, but punish the Petitioners of another kinde, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204627:14"/> colour, That it is a Crime, That they are not satisfied with your sense; as if you were onely trusted by the people of one opinion, to take all pains to publish and print Petitions which agree with your wishes, though they were never presented, and to use the same Industry and Authority to keep those that indeed were presented and avowed from being published (though by Our own Authority) because the Argument is not pleasant to you, to pretend impartiality and infallibility, and to expresse the greatest Passion and Affection in the Order of your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, and no lesse errour and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>understanding in your Iudgements and Resolutions.</p>
            <p>He doth remember well the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of his Trust, and of his Oath, and desires that you will do so too, and your own solemn Vow and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation, and then you will not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think it convenient, but necessary to give his Majestie a full reparation for all the Scandals laid upon him,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204627:15"/> and all the scandalous Positions made against him; and that it is lesse disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to retract Errors, then by avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to confesse the Malice of them, and will see this to be the surest way for the preservation of the Protestant Religion, the redemption of your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the happinesse and prosperity of your selves, and all Our Dominions, and of the dignitie and freedom of Parliament.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:204627:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>